[music]
When I took the most I ever had, I was
awake for a whole week.
>> I gave myself an injection and as soon
as I pulled the syringe, [music] my body
was already thrilled.
[music]
>> Sorry.
[snorts]
>> [snorts and gasps]
>> Yeah, everything's fine.
>> Everything's all right.
>> I was 14 when math came into the
picture.
>> I just know that she started at 13, so
really really early.
Crystal meth is one of the world's most
dangerous drugs. It's cheap to produce,
extremely addictive, and has serious
health consequences.
Few other drugs have such a reputation
for ruining lives.
Historically, math use in Europe [music]
has been relatively low compared to the
US and Asia. European math used to be
concentrated in Shezekia where usage is
still highest in Europe. But in recent
years, consumption across Europe has
risen. Some areas such as Eastern
Germany are particularly affected. Five
of Europe's 15 highest math use cities
are located there.
here in particular [music] and who is
profiting from all of this. We traveled
to Eastern Germany and spoke with
experts and former users. These
conversations were originally conducted
in German. For this video, we have
provided dubbing and subtitles. At the
same time, we try to understand where
this drug comes from, what other areas
of Europe are experiencing an increase,
and what insidious global structures are
behind the crystal meth trade.
>> [music]
>> It's a cold New Year's Eve in a town in
Saxony. Dominic comes from a stable
family. At this point, he's 14 years
old. He's out celebrating with friends.
They decide to buy weed from an
acquaintance for €80, but the dealer
doesn't have any left. Instead, he
offers them a choice. They can keep
their €80 or use it to try something
else.
>> Crystal meth.
>> We tried the crystal without thinking
about it. I thought it was funny and
just took it for fun.
>> It won't be the last time. We did it
again the next weekend and then
regularly every other weekend and then
daily. We started out snorting it, but
it it really burns your nose. And at
first that was still manageable, but
after a while it got so painful that we
had to find other ways to get our fix.
So, uh we smoked it, we drank it,
parachuted it. Parachuting a drug
involves wrapping it in thin paper and
swallowing it. Over time, the drug's
effects get weaker and weaker. Dominic
is developing a tolerance.
>> After a while, uh, the effect wasn't the
same. My body was too used to it. The
only thing left was injecting it to get
the most out of the drug. It's almost
the way to get the most bang for your
buck.
>> Intravenous use involves dissolving the
methan water and injecting it with a
needle straight into the veins. At this
point, Dominic is 15 years old. I gave
myself an injection and as soon as I
pulled up the syringe, my body was
already thrilled. As soon as I felt it
coarse through my veins, my mind went,
you know, you you jump up, you're wide
awake, you're immediately on the go,
you're totally you're outgoing, you're
chatty. This feeling was just you you
just feel great and active and like you
could move mountains.
Dominic tells us this first injection
was the best high of his life. Thanks to
the drug, I didn't feel alone. And with
these people, I never felt excluded. I
was never alone.
[music]
It's 1938. The pharmaceutical company
Tla introduces the drug peine to the
German market. Available without a
prescription, it contains a novel
substance, methampetamin, the active
ingredient of crystal meth. Pevitine is
marketed as a stimulant, a wakeup pill.
It quickly becomes a bestseller in
Germany.
>> A candy company even launches chocolates
that contain pevitin. They're set to
help with so-called housewife
depression. Three to nine chocolates a
day are set to do the trick. Nine
chocolates contain about the same amount
of methamphetamine as is needed for an
average methi.
It's not long until the Nazis start
using pevitine. By the 1939 invasion of
Poland, they'd already used it millions
of times. It's a miracle drug for the
Blitz Creek. Fear, hunger, fatigue, all
fade away on meth. Soldiers are more
aggressive in combat. But soon, the drug
side effects become impossible to
ignore.
In 1941, pevitine becomes prescription
only. Still, it remains widely
accessible. After the Second World War,
doctors in both East and West Germany
continue to prescribe it as a stimulant
and pickme up. Athletes use it for
performance enhancement.
In the 1970s, the UN classifies
methamphetamine as a schedule 2 drug,
which outlaws its unauthorized
production and sale. Its usage declines
throughout Europe. In Germany, pevitine
remains on the market until 1988, when
medical use of meth becomes illegal.
Nowadays, the street name for illegally
cooked meth is often still pevitin.
Soon, a black market emerges. Small meth
labs start producing crystal meth
themselves, mostly in the US and Eastern
Europe. And by the 1990s, illegally
cooked meth finds its way from Eastern
Europe to the rest of the continent.
Every addiction has an origin story.
Ashley's starts at age 20. I was [music]
having some financial difficulties at
the time and I have a daughter. I had
her father take care of her until I
could sort out my money problems, but I
haven't gotten her back since. That was
a turning point for me when I said to
myself, I need to get on a [music]
different track.
>> Ashley also wishes to remain anonymous,
so we've changed her name. She first
comes into contact with me through her
sister.
>> My sister's been using it basically her
whole life, and at one point she took me
along with her. She started at about 13,
so really really early. At first, it
[music] it wasn't that much. I'd say I
did a line every couple of days, maybe
every other day.
And it works. Well, sort of. Math
[music] distracts her, takes her mind
off things.
>> For one thing, it keeps you wide awake.
One time I was taking it and I didn't
sleep for a whole week. And it still
made me feel even more energetic. It was
mostly that [music] I just didn't feel
anything anymore. I didn't care about
anything. And after a point, it was
really often. I was definitely using at
least a gram a day. By then, [music] I
honestly didn't care anymore.
Math begins to take up more and more
space in Dominic's life. Everyone only
[music] cared about the drug. That's how
it went. You're focused. You're
inventive. It's just, it's insane.
Staying up night [music] after night
doing this and that, and it just keeps
going on and on and on. I spent
everything I had on it. Poured all my
money into using sometimes several
hundred in a day.
In my case, I had a good relationship
with my dealer. I only paid €25 a gram,
which just made me use even more.
>> As Dominic's [music] Matthew use
increases, he needs new ways to get his
fix. At first, I just bought it from a
dealer or somebody went to get it for
me. By the time I was 16, that didn't
work anymore. I was using way more than
I could afford. Started driving to the
Czech Republic to pick up there.
The exact production [music] cost of a
gram of meth is hard to pin down. But in
Czecha, the hub of Europe's meth
production, you can get it for as little
as 10 to 20. Czech authorities report
that around 6 and 12 tons of crystal
meth are produced in the country each
year. In 2022 alone, police shut down
more than 200 illegal meth labs. The
country does not only lead in
production. It also has some of the
highest consumption rates in Europe.
Producing meth requires both the right
equipment and expertise in chemistry. In
Shezia, a country with a strong
pharmaceutical industry, you can easily
find both. Every math cook also needs
ephedrin, the base ingredient used to
make me math amphetamine. In Czecha,
ephedrin is tightly [music] regulated
because of the meth trade. But just
across the border in Poland, ephedrin
based medications such as cold medicine
can be bought in bulk over the counter.
That's where many Czech math cooks
source their supply. Meth cooked in
Shezekia easily makes its way into
Germany. Smuggling it across the border
is a lucrative business, whether through
big dealers or in countless small
shipments.
>> [music]
>> there. I was taken along by older guys.
We called them old junkies who were
basically just there to do the [music]
driving. And of course, there's the
check dealers. You just go to any pickup
spot and they'll be there. But I also
drove right into [music] the country and
picked it up directly from the lab. We
swallowed it, packed it into little
parachutes, [music] and smuggled it over
the border in our bodies. According to
Czech police, in 2014, about 1/3 of
Czech meth ended up in Germany. Recent
analyses show that methamphetamine
residues in the wastewater of East
German cities are especially [music]
high.
We asked Ashley and Dominic, how long
does it take to get meth where they
live?
>> I'd say maybe half an hour. I wouldn't
[music] say longer than that. I'd say it
doesn't even take 5 minutes. In Keitowl,
Dresden, Leapig, the scene is well
established there. You you can just tell
you know exactly where to go. According
to Sax and government officials,
Matthews and the state isn't increasing,
but it's plateaued at a very high level.
To understand how underground markets
work, many moving parts have to come
together. The bigger story emerges
through collaboration among research
institutions, governments, journalists,
and above all, the voices of those
directly affected. We're grateful to the
brave individuals who have shared their
stories with us and for the sponsors who
make our investigations possible. This
video is brought to you by Anidesk, a
powerful tool for seamless
collaboration. Anyes gives you secure
remote access to your devices from
anywhere in the world. It makes file
transfer, troubleshooting, or
collaborative work super simple. What we
love about Anyesk is that it's powerful
enough for highle creative work. You can
access your editing rig remotely and
scrub video or audio in real time. Its
proprietary codec keeps latency low and
visuals sharp. And it works on basically
any device, so you're never locked out
of your setup. Plus, with 99.98%
uptime, you can rely on stable
connections whenever you need them. Try
Anyesk for free at any.com/fern.
[music]
It's 2014. By now, Dominic is a legal
adult. He's been using math [music]
regularly for several years. No job, no
university. He's no longer following
conventional [music] life paths. He's
firmly in the grip of addiction. and it
costs him several thousand [music] per
month. That level of consumption needs
to be financed somehow
[music]
in my circle for sure through petty
crime, individual [music] offenses,
group efforts. I got myself into a lot
of trouble with the law.
>> The more math he uses, the more crimes
he commits.
>> I I started out shoplifting and let's
just say I ended up in [music] much
bigger trouble. It just got worse and
worse.
>> So bad he wound up in prison.
[laughter]
>> This is Dr. Stefan Mule. He's a
professor of clinical psychology and
addiction researcher and works with meth
users.
He explains to us why methamphetamine is
so addictive.
Methamphetamine floods the brain with
dopamine, the chemical that regulates
lust, motivation, and your brain's
reward system. It's often nicknamed the
feelgood hormone. On average, an orgasm
triggers an [music] 80% increase in
dopamine release.
In other words, a single hit of meth can
release 17 times more of the pleasure
hormone than an orgasm.
>> [music]
>> The first time someone tries [music]
meth is enough to lay the foundation for
addiction. How quickly that risk turns
into full-blown addiction depends on how
the drug is consumed. In simple terms,
the faster [music] meth reaches the
brain, the higher the risk of addiction.
Swallowing it takes about 20 minutes for
the effects to kick in. Smoking it takes
only [music] 5 to 7 seconds. The same
goes for injection.
Once the high wears off, what follows is
a brutal crash.
[music]
See,
>> Dominic and Ashley each find their own
way to endure withdrawal symptoms.
>> I slept for a week, only waking up a few
times to drink something. What I
remember is constantly [music] breaking
into sweats and having heart and
circulation problems from not hydrating
enough.
>> I can only say from my own experience
[music] that you just get very tired or
you sleep a lot. During that time, I was
also severely underweight. Sometimes I
didn't eat at all, only when I'd come
down a bit. for
withdrawal can feel so miserable that it
seems only one thing can help. Getting
high again, a vicious cycle.
Regular long-term use of methamphetamine
can lead to serious health problems
including depression, [music] heart
attacks, and epilepsy. by
[music]
the body deteriorates. Poor skin, severe
weight loss, bad teeth. Over time, meth
damages organs and causes brain damage.
Here's
a map of all the meth labs that were
shut down in Europe between 2018 and
2020. It's clear here that shea is a
major stronghold in Europe. In Germany,
Bavaria and the east are most affected.
But further west, you can see that the
Netherlands, Belgium, Norway, and Sweden
are also established meth hotspots.
Large amounts of crystal meth in the EU
now come from the Netherlands or Mexico.
It's believed that [music] Mexican drug
cartels drive a lot of this traffic,
using their expertise to cook meth in
Dutch and Belgian labs, while precursor
chemicals are smuggled into Europe from
China. By now, the drug is firmly
entrenched throughout Europe, [music]
and it shows no signs of disappearing
anytime soon. Traffickers exploit
international trade routes, [music]
airplanes, cargo ships, trucks. If one
route gets shut down, another opens up.
Occasionally, authorities report
successes against drug traffickers, but
the larger battle is widely considered
unwinable.
Between 2010 and 2020, the quantity of
confiscated methamphetamine increased
nearly sixfold in the EU. One researcher
in the European Union Drugs Agency warns
that currently there are indications of
increased methamphetamine use all
throughout Europe. Wastewater analysis
confirms an increase of consumption in
many European countries.
Fast forward to 2023. Ashley's been
using Crystal Math for 2 years now.
She's been homeless at times and has
given up custody of her daughter. She's
lost contact with family and former
friends. Today, she's using meth again,
but this time something's different. She
feels unwell and realizes she can't
properly talk.
After using, I wasn't in control of
myself. I struggled to speak. I knew
what I wanted to say, but I couldn't get
the words out. Instead, I just sat there
staring into nothing.
>> She calls an ambulance. Shortly after,
she's admitted into psychiatric
hospital.
>> That in and of itself was a reason to
quit, but then I found out I was
pregnant, and that was the real reason.
Sorry.
[snorts]
People struggling with addiction have
[music] various ways to find support.
Often the first points of contact are
community outreach volunteers or social
workers. They help users with everyday
struggles like finding a [music] place
to live. But just as importantly, they
support young people in taking the
difficult steps out of addiction. By
2021, Dominic [music] reached a breaking
point. I noticed suicidal behavior in
myself, deliberately giving myself
overdoses. Other problems added to it as
well. Physically, I could feel it.
either I kept going with the drugs and I
would probably die soon or [music] I
changed something and I I wanted to
change. He decides to start addiction
therapy.
Beating a crystal meth addiction usually
means facing a long and difficult
[music] journey.
The first step is withdrawal. It takes
about 4 to 6 [music] weeks for the body
to overcome a physical dependence.
Afterwards, therapy can begin. We travel
to a rehab center close to the Czech
border [music] to understand how it all
works. This is Uva Vika. He runs the
clinic.
Springfield.
Addiction therapy in Veha's clinic takes
place in three successive phases. An
orientation phase, an intensive phase,
and a reintegration phase. After
physical detox, the therapy focuses on
building awareness of the patterns that
led someone to use the drug. Patients
work on strategies to cope with
difficult emotions and triggers. At the
same time, they are prepared for life
after rehab. It's not only about getting
clean, but also about staying clean. For
starters, this means leaving your old
life behind.
[music]
It's also about developing a whole new
perspective on life.
>> And patients have to prepare for
difficult faces ahead.
>> [music]
>> Addiction memory can be treacherous. The
danger of relapse lurks everywhere, even
in places where you would least expect
it. [music]
It's 2014. Dominic's [music] been in
prison for over a year and a half. You
might think he's long gone through
detox. Think again.
>> In fact, there are both [music] officers
and inmates who smuggle it in, either
through visits or through the officers
themselves, depending on what the
officer earns from it.
In my prison, it was basically the norm.
You could almost say that there were
more drugs inside the prison than
[music] outside. In prisons across
Europe, it's clear inmates are routinely
getting high. Drugs are regularly found
and seized by authorities and show up in
urine tests. Supplying a closed off
prison population with drugs may present
dealers with added logistical
challenges, but the demand is high.
Drugs sold in prisons sometimes fetch
four times the profits than those sold
on the outside.
[music] Beyond visitors and prison
officers, Dominic also tells us about
others you might not normally associate
with crystal meth.
Another common way to get drugs is
through the prison's priest. He brings
in a lot of substances.
>> We were also not able to independently
verify these claims. We reached out to
[music] Saxony justice authorities but
received no response. Dominic also tells
us that even outside prison, some police
officers will turn a blind eye to
crystal meth. I never once got reported
for meth possession. They never filed
charges. When I'd be sitting with my
dealers, sometimes cops would come in to
pick up their own stuff, and we'd know
about raids ahead of time. We'd get the
heads up a day or so before a raid,
[music]
so we had time to stash stuff away. We
were also not able to independently
verify these claims. Prison guards,
priests, even police officers. Dominic's
accounts, if true, show just how deeply
methamphetamine has penetrated all
layers of society.
Methampetamin has a certain reputation.
>> But the more experts we spoke with, the
more complexity we found. Meth is used
not only by marginalized communities
impacted by poverty, but Europeans from
all walks of life.
According to Dr. Muik, some use math for
neuro enhancement. They find that math
can boost [music] performance at
university or on the job.
>> [laughter]
>> They have to do a lot of repetitive
tasks like sitting for hours on a
tractor plowing the fields.
For
me,
then there's the classic party context
where meth is used like ecstasy or
cocaine. There's also a pretty sealed
off scene called chemex. These are
groups where people meet in closed
circles for sex parties.
The strongly sexualizing effect of meth
comes with a whole host of other
problems, particularly for female users.
It's not uncommon for female methusers
to keep using while pregnant. This can
lead to prenatal damage and neonatal
impairments. The fetus can be severely
harmed and born with limitations or
sometimes serious disabilities.
Of the 35,000 children born in Saxony in
2015, 160 to 180 were diagnosed with
damage caused by the drug. And these are
just the reported cases. The undiagnosed
number may be even higher.
When Ashley finds out she's pregnant,
it's a huge wakeup call. It changes
[music]
everything
for me. That was really the turning
point. When I found out I was pregnant,
I didn't want to keep going. I knew
[music] I would be harming my child. And
that was the moment I said, "It's it's
now or never."
>> Yeah, [music] I am. My boyfriend
supported me. He said I could go to
therapy and I would have done it but
ultimately I overcame my addiction
without the pregnancy [music] gave me so
much strength I could handle all of it
and take care of my daughter that was
easy for me in the end. Ashley managed
[music] to quit meth without addiction
therapy. She gave birth to a healthy
baby who she tells us is developing
well.
Both Dominic and Ashley [music] have
left me math behind and are leading
lives free from the drug.
[music]
>> [music]
>> Never again. Never ever again.
>> Their stories show that the journey to
recovery is [music] absolutely
worthwhile.
I believe anyone can quit. But of
course, you have to find the will to do
it within yourself.
[music]
for
anyone struggling with methamphetamine
[music] addiction can seek support from
friends and family, from community
outreach workers, [music] or through
local addiction counseling services.
Links to online resources can be found
in the description.
When I look back to the time [music] I
was using, my world was so gray. Since I
stopped using my world is full of color
again. I enjoy [music] life again. I can
enjoy the small things like when an old
lady smiles at me. You can appreciate
these things way more if you don't use